<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>
    <name>Gedit Technology</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/feed.atom.xml</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/feed.atom.xml" />
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/index.html" />
  <title>Gedit Technology</title>
  <updated>2025-11-14T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <icon>https://gedit-text-editor.org/images/gedit-icon-16x16.png</icon>

<entry>
  <title>Mid-November News</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-11-14-mid-november-news.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-11-14-mid-november-news.html" />
  <published>2025-11-14T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-11-14T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  Misc news about the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">gedit text editor</a>,
  mid-November edition!
  <!-- (Some sections are a bit technical). -->
</p>

<h3>Website: new design</h3>
<p>
  Probably the highlight this month is the new design of the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">gedit website</a>.
</p>
<p>
  If it looks familiar to some of you, it's normal, it's because it's an
  adaptation of the previous GtkSourceView website that was developed in the old
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/Archive/gnomeweb-wml" target="_blank">gnomeweb-wml</a>
  repository. gnomeweb-wml (projects.gnome.org) is what predates all the wiki
  pages for
  <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps" target="_blank">Apps</a>
  and
  <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Projects" target="_blank">Projects</a>.
  The wiki has been retired, so another solution had to be found.
</p>
<p>
  For the timeline, projects.gnome.org was available until 2013/2014 where all
  the content had been migrated to the wiki. Then the wiki has been retired in
  2024.
</p>
<p>
  Note that there are still rough edges on the gedit website, and more
  importantly some efforts still need to be done to bring the old CSS stylesheet
  forward to the new(-ish) responsive web design world.
</p>

<p>
  For the most nostalgic of you:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20131212061032/projects.gnome.org/gedit/"
         target="_blank">gedit website in 2013</a>
      (<code>projects.gnome.org/gedit/</code> on web.archive.org)
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="images/2025-11-14/screenshot-gedit-website-in-2013.png"
         target="_blank"><img src="images/2025-11-14/thumbnail-screenshot-gedit-website-in-2013.png"
                              alt="Screenshot of gedit website in 2013" /></a>
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>
      <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20131215224242/projects.gnome.org/gtksourceview/"
         target="_blank">GtkSourceView website in 2013</a>
      (<code>projects.gnome.org/gtksourceview/</code> on web.archive.org)
    </p>
    <p>
      <a href="images/2025-11-14/screenshot-gtksourceview-website-in-2013.png"
         target="_blank"><img src="images/2025-11-14/thumbnail-screenshot-gtksourceview-website-in-2013.png"
                              alt="Screenshot of GtkSourceView website in 2013" /></a>
    </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  And for the <em>least</em> nostalgic of you:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>gedit website from last month (October 2025)</p>
    <p>
      <a href="images/2025-11-14/screenshot-gedit-website-in-october-2025.png"
         target="_blank"><img src="images/2025-11-14/thumbnail-screenshot-gedit-website-in-october-2025.png"
                              alt="Screenshot of gedit website in October 2025" /></a>
    </p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  What we can say is that the gedit project has stood the test of time!
</p>

<h3>Enter TeX: improved search and replace</h3>
<p>
  Some context: I would like some day to unify the search and replace feature
  between Enter TeX and gedit. It needs to retain the best of each.
</p>
<p>
  In Enter TeX it's a combined horizontal bar, something that I would like in
  gedit too to replace the dialog window that occludes part of the text.
</p>
<p>
  In gedit the strengths include: the search-as-you-type possibility, and a
  history of past searches. Both are missing in Enter TeX. (These are not the
  only things that need to be retained; the same workflows, keyboard shortcuts
  etc. are also an integral part of the functionality).
</p>
<p>
  So to work towards that goal, I started in Enter TeX. I merged around 50
  commits in the git repository for this change already, rewriting in C (from
  Vala) some parts and improving the UI along the way. The code needs to be in C
  because it'll be moved to libgedit-tepl so that it can be consumed by gedit
  easily.
</p>
<p>
  Here is how it looks:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2025-11-14/screenshot-enter-tex-search-and-replace.png"
     target="_blank"><img src="images/2025-11-14/screenshot-enter-tex-search-and-replace.png"
                          width="250"
                          alt="Screenshot of the search and replace in Enter TeX" /></a>
</p>

<h3>Internal refactoring for GeditWindow and its statusbar</h3>
<p>
  GeditWindow is what we can call a god class. It is too big, both in the number
  of lines and the number of instance variables.
</p>
<p>
  So this month I've continued to refactor it, to extract a GeditWindowStatus
  class. There was already a GeditStatusbar class, but its features have now
  been moved to libgedit-tepl as TeplStatusbar.
</p>
<p>
  GeditWindowStatus takes up the responsibility to create the TeplStatusbar, to
  fill it with the indicators and other buttons, and to make the connection with
  GeditWindow and the current tab/document.
</p>
<p>
  So as a result, GeditWindow is a little less omniscient ;-)
</p>

<h3>As a conclusion</h3>
<p>
  gedit does not materialize out of empty space; it takes time to develop and
  maintain. To demonstrate your appreciation of this piece of software and help
  its future development, remember that you can
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/donations.html" target="_blank">fund the project</a>.
  Your support is critical and much appreciated.
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Mid-October News</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-10-15-mid-october-news.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-10-15-mid-october-news.html" />
  <published>2025-10-15T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-10-15T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  Misc news about the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">gedit text editor</a>,
  mid-October edition! (Some sections are a bit technical).
</p>

<h3>Rework of the file loading and saving (continued)</h3>
<p>
  The refactoring continues in the libgedit-gtksourceview module, this time to
  tackle a big class that takes too much responsibilities. A utility is in
  development which will permit to delegate a part of the work.
</p>
<p>
  The utility is about character encoding conversion, with support of invalid
  bytes. It takes as input a single GBytes (the file content), and transforms it
  into a list of chunks. A chunk contains either valid (successfully converted)
  bytes, or invalid bytes. The output format - the "list of chunks" - is subject
  to change to improve memory consumption and performances.
</p>
<p>
  Note that invalid bytes are allowed, to be able to open really any kind of
  files with gedit.
</p>
<p>
  I must also note that this is quite sensitive work, at the heart of document
  loading for gedit. Normally all these refactorings and improvements will be
  worth it!
</p>

<h3>Progress in other modules</h3>
<p>
  There has been some progress on other modules:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>gedit:</strong> version 48.1.1 has been released with a few minor
    updates.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>The Flatpak</strong> on Flathub: update to gedit 48.1.1 and the
    GNOME 49 runtime.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>gspell:</strong> version 1.14.1 has been released, mainly to pick up
    the updated translations.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>GitHub Sponsors</h3>
<p>
  In addition to Liberapay, you can now support the work that I do on
  GitHub Sponsors. See the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/donations.html" target="_blank">gedit donations</a>
  page.
</p>
<p>
  Thank you ❤️
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Mid-September News</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-09-15-mid-september-news.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-09-15-mid-september-news.html" />
  <published>2025-09-15T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-09-15T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  Misc news about the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">gedit</a>
  text editor, mid-September edition! (Some sections are a bit technical).
</p>

<h3>Next version will be released when Ready</h3>
<p>
  While the release of GNOME 49.0 was approaching (it's this week!), I came to
  the conclusion that it's best for gedit to wait more, and to follow the Debian
  way of releasing software: when it's Ready. "Ready" with an uppercase letter
  'R'!
</p>
<p>
  So the question is: what is <em>not</em> ready? Two main things:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    The rework of the file loading and saving: it is something that takes time,
    and I prefer to be sure that it'll be a solid solution.
  </li>
  <li>
    The question about the Python support for implementing plugins. Time will
    tell what is the answer.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>Rework of the file loading and saving (next steps)</h3>
<p>
  Work continues to refactor that part of the code, both in
  libgedit-gtksourceview and gedit.
</p>
<p>
  I won't go into too much technical details this time. But what the previous
  developer (Ignacio Casal Quinteiro, aka nacho)
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit/-/commit/89fe90084cfa3c727589fafa969a9678208a8652" target="_blank">wrote</a>
  (in 2011) in a comment at the top of a class is
  <em>"welcome to a really big headache."</em>
</p>
<p>
  And naturally, I want to improve the situation. For a long time this class was
  used as a black box, using only its interface. Time has come to change things!
  It takes time, but I already see the end of the tunnel and I have good hopes
  that the code will be better structured. I intend to write about it more once
  finished.
</p>
<p>
  But I can reveal that there is already a visible improvement: loading a big
  file (e.g. 200 MB) is now super fast! Previously, it could take one minute to
  load such file, with a progress bar shown and a Cancel button. Now there is
  not enough time to even click on (or to see) the Cancel button! (I'm talking
  about local files, for remote files with a slow network connection, the
  progress bar is still useful).
</p>
<p>
  To be continued...
</p>

<p><small>
  If you appreciate the work that I do, you can send
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/donations.html" target="_blank">a thank-you donation</a>.
  Your support is much appreciated! For years to come, it will be useful for the
  project.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Donating to the gedit project</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-08-30-donating-to-the-gedit-project.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-08-30-donating-to-the-gedit-project.html" />
  <published>2025-08-30T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-08-30T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  A short news to announce that you can now donate to the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">gedit text editor</a>
  project!
</p>
<p>
  Donations will be used to continue the development and maintenance of the
  application and its plugins.
</p>
<p>
  If you like gedit, your support is much appreciated! For years to come, it
  will be useful for the project.
</p>
<p>
  <a href="https://liberapay.com/swilmet/" target="_blank"><img src="images/liberapay-donate.svg" alt="Donate using Liberapay" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  Thanks!
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Mid-August News</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-08-14-mid-august-news.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-08-14-mid-august-news.html" />
  <published>2025-08-14T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-08-14T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  Misc news about the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">gedit</a>
  text editor, mid-August edition! (Some sections are a bit technical).
</p>

<h3>Code Comment plugin rewritten</h3>
<p>
  I forgot to talk about it in the mid-July news, but the Code Comment plugin
  has been rewritten in C (it was previously implemented in Python) and the bulk
  of it is implemented as re-usable code in libgedit-tepl. The implementation is
  now shared between
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/enter-tex" target="_blank">Enter TeX</a>
  and gedit.
</p>

<h3>File loading and saving: a new GtkSourceEncoding class</h3>
<p>
  I've modified the GtkSourceEncoding class that is part of
  libgedit-gtksourceview, and adapted gedit accordingly.
  The new version of GtkSourceEncoding comes from an experiment that I did in
  libgedit-tepl several years ago.
</p>
<p>
  GtkSourceEncoding represents a character set (or "charset" for short). It is
  used in combination with <code>iconv</code> to convert text files from one
  encoding to another (for example from ISO-8859-15 to UTF-8).
</p>
<p>
  The purpose of the experiment that was done in libgedit-tepl (the TeplEncoding
  class) was to accomodate the needs for a
  <a href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/uchardet/" target="_blank">uchardet</a>
  usage (note that uchardet is not yet used by gedit, but it would be useful).
  uchardet is a library to automatically detect the encoding of some input text.
  It returns an iconv-compatible charset, as a string.
</p>
<p>
  It is <em>this string</em> - returned by uchardet - that we want to store and
  pass to <code>iconv</code> unmodified, to not lose information.
</p>
<p>
  The problem with the old version of GtkSourceEncoding: there was a fixed set
  of GtkSourceEncoding instances, all <code>const</code> (so without the need to
  free them). When trying to get an instance for an unknown charset string, NULL
  was returned. So this was not appropriate for a uchardet usage (or at least,
  not a clean solution: with the charset string returned by uchardet it was not
  guaranteed that a corresponding GtkSourceEncoding instance was available).
</p>
<p>
  Since GtkSourceEncoding is used in a lot of places, we don't want to change
  the code to represent a charset as just a string. And a simple string is
  anyway too basic, GtkSourceEncoding provides useful features.
</p>
<p>
  So, long story short: the new GtkSourceEncoding class returns new instances
  that must be freed, and has a constructor that just makes a copy of the
  charset string (there is the <code>get_charset()</code> method to get back the
  string, unmodified).
</p>
<p>
  So gedit can keep using the GtkSourceEncoding abstraction, and we are one step
  closer to being able to use uchardet or something similar!
</p>

<h3>Know more about the gedit's maintainer</h3>
<p>
  I now have a personal web site, or more accurately a single web
  <em>page</em>:<br />
  <a href="https://wilmet-software.be/" target="_blank">wilmet-software.be</a>
  (Sébastien Wilmet)
</p>
<p>
  gedit is a 27-years-old project, the first lines were written in 1998
  (and <em>normally</em> it won't be part of the
  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/27_Club" target="_blank">27 Club</a>!).
  I've been a contributor to the project for 14 years, so more than half the
  project existence. Time flies!
</p>

<h3>Robust file loading - some progress</h3>
<p>
  After the rework of GtkSourceEncoding (which is part of the File Loading and
  Saving subsystem in libgedit-gtksourceview), I've made good progress to make
  the file loading more robust - although there is more work still to do.
</p>
<p>
  It is a basis in programming to check all program input. gedit makes things a
  bit harder to accomplish this. To open a <em>document</em>:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    There is first the problem of the character encoding. It is
    not sufficient for a general-purpose text editor to accept only UTF-8. So
    text files can be almost anything in binary form.
  </li>
  <li>
    Then gedit allows to open documents containing
    invalid characters in the specified or auto-detected
    encoding. With this, documents can <em>really</em> be anything in binary
    form.
  </li>
  <li>
    Finally the GtkTextView widget used at the heart of gedit has several
    limitations: (1) very big files (like log files or database dumps) are not
    supported, a limit on the content size must be set (and if reached, still
    allow to load the file with truncated content). (2) very long lines cause
    performance problems and can freeze the application.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  So, the good news is that progress has been made on this. (There is only a
  good news, let's stay positive!).
</p>

<p><small>
  If you appreciate the work that I do in gedit, I would like to know your
  feedback, what I should improve or which important feature is missing. You can
  contact me
  <a href="https://wilmet-software.be/" target="_blank">by email</a>
  for example, or on a
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/" target="_blank">discussion channel</a>.
  Thank you :-) !
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Mid-July News</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-07-14-mid-july-news.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-07-14-mid-july-news.html" />
  <published>2025-07-14T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-07-14T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  Misc news about the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a>
  text editor, mid-July edition! (Some sections are a bit technical).
</p>

<h3>gedit 49 in preparation</h3>
<p>
  About version numbers: if all goes well, gedit 49 will match GNOME 49 and are
  expected for September! So gedit will be back on track to follow the GNOME
  version numbers. This is after some trials to <em>not</em> follow them, to
  release gedit versions when ready and more often, but at the end of the day
  this doesn't change much.
</p>

<h3>Gedit Development Guidelines</h3>
<p>
  I've written the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit/-/tree/master/docs/guidelines">Gedit Development Guidelines</a>,
  a series of small Markdown documents. It regroups the information in one
  place. It also documents stuff that needed to be written in commit messages,
  so to avoid repetition and to have more complete explanations, commit messages
  can now refer to the guideline documents.
</p>
<p>
  Be warned that some of the gedit guidelines don't follow the more modern GNOME
  development practices. The rationales are clearly explained. In my humble
  opinion, what is deemed "modern" doesn't automatically make something better.
  (If you read this and <em>are</em> a developer of one of the modern things not
  used by gedit, take it as a user feedback, and remember that what truly
  matters is that the GTK development platform is still appreciated!).
</p>

<h3>Improved preferences</h3>
<p>
  <a href="images/2025-07-14/prefs-reset.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2025-07-14/prefs-reset.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot - reset all preferences"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2025-07-14/prefs-spell-checker.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2025-07-14/prefs-spell-checker.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot - spell-checker preferences"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  There is now a "Reset All..." button in the Preferences dialog. And it is now
  possible to configure the default language used by the spell-checker.
</p>

<h3>Python plugins</h3>
<p>
  Most Linux distributions ship some older versions of some GNOME modules to
  make Python plugins in gedit (and other apps) still work. There has been some
  disturbances in the air, but my hope is that everything will be back to normal
  for GNOME 49.
</p>

<h3>File loading and saving</h3>
<p>
  There are some known issues with the file loading implementation, and I'm
  working on it.
</p>
<p>
  About the old <code>iconv()</code> function, I've created a utility class called
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/libgedit-gtksourceview/-/blob/main/gtksourceview/file-loading-and-saving/gtksourceiconv.c" target="_blank">GtkSourceIconv</a>
  to (try to) tame the beast, except that the beast <em>cannot be fully
  tamed</em>, by design! Some aspects of its API are broken, and what I
  recommend for new code is to look at the libICU to see if it's better.
  (gtksourceiconv.c has a comment at the top with more details).
</p>
<p>
  But instead of doing ground-breaking changes in the file loading and saving
  code (to switch to the libICU), I prefer a more incremental approach, and this
  means to still use <code>iconv()</code> (for the time being at least). The
  advantage is that incremental changes are directly useful and used; progress
  is made on gedit!
</p>
<p>
  I attempted a while back a new implementation in libgedit-tepl (TeplEncoding,
  TeplFile, etc). The problem is that I created a different API, so switching
  the whole of gedit to it was more difficult. And the new implementation lacked
  several important features used by gedit.
</p>
<p>
  Now I'm moving some of my experiments done in libgedit-tepl back to
  libgedit-gtksourceview, because it's the latter (GtkSourceEncoding,
  GtkSourceFile, etc) that is used by gedit's file loading and saving machinery.
  libgedit-gtksourceview doesn't guarantee a stable API, and I consider it part
  of gedit, so it's more <em>malleable code</em> :-)
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Some problems currently with Python and gedit plugins</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-04-30-no-more-pythons-in-gedit.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-04-30-no-more-pythons-in-gedit.html" />
  <published>2025-04-30T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-04-30T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  <strong>UPDATE:</strong> if libpeas1 gets ported to the latest version of
  GIRepository, then it would be possible to re-enable the Python support in
  gedit. But <em>only for third-party plugins</em>. That way we keep the best of
  both worlds. The plugins shipped by gedit itself (the "official" plugins) will
  be written only in C, but Rust would be welcome too if someone figures out how
  to write a libpeas-based plugin in Rust. For most users this means that some
  official plugins will be missing. For third-party plugin developers, this
  means that a full rewrite of the plugin would not be necessary. Here is the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit/-/issues/618">GitLab issue</a>
  where this is discussed.
</p>

<p><br /></p>

<p>
  The first <code>*.py</code> file in the
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a> repository was added in
  2005, 20 years ago.
  Since then, it seems that it has always been possible to write gedit plugins
  in Python. Well, this is no more.
</p>
<p>
  It deserves some explanation.
</p>

<h3>Reducing the number of programming languages to deal with</h3>
<p>
  A multi-language project is much harder to manage.
  Now gedit only uses C and a little of Objective-C for the macOS support.
  The libgedit-* are entirely written in C.
</p>
<p>
  There was a Vala plugin (Find in Files) but has been
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit-plugins/-/commit/7d33fb7a667c738f5089d951ea8b0bba5cc6b968">removed in 2022</a>
  (unfortunately there is no replacement).
  The commit message already mentions the difficulty of working with multiple
  languages. So the problem is not new.
</p>

<h3>Other reasons</h3>
<p>
  Making it easier to package gedit on Windows, avoiding the need to bundle a
  whole Python interpreter with the app. This also makes the package smaller and
  the app launches more quickly (better performances).
</p>
<p>
  There are also some inherent difficulties to maintain large Python codebases
  in the long run. gedit plugins are not specifically large, but still, the
  difficulties were present. (If Python is your thing, you may have a different
  experience and opinion. That's fine, there needs to be something for
  everybody).
</p>
<p>
  So over the recent years a few plugins have been rewritten from Python to C
  already. With the final goal of phasing out the Python support. This was a
  slow process, until ...
</p>

<h3>Some PyGObject and GIRepository updates later</h3>
<p>
  GNOME 48 released in March comes with an update that basically makes all
  Python plugins unusable in gedit. It's more related to the code dealing with
  the <em>loading</em> of plugins, not the plugins themselves.
</p>
<p>
  More precisely, the latest version of PyGObject made the Python 3 loader of
  libpeas1 unusable (libpeas provides the plugin engine for gedit and other
  apps). libpeas1 and gedit depend on GIRepository-2.0 while the latest version
  of PyGObject has upgraded to GIRepository-3.0. It is not possible to use both
  GIRepository-2.0 and 3.0 at the same time in the same process.
  (<a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/pygobject/-/issues/686">Link to the issue</a>).
</p>
<p>
  It's like weeds growing. If you do nothing, weeds grow and regression bugs
  happen. Note that it doesn't mean that nothing is done in gedit, there is
  still development done. But the GTK and GNOME platform apparently moves
  faster.
</p>
<p>
  gedit is <em>no longer</em> developed and maintained by a team of 5-6
  dedicated hackers. So the project is no longer able to lead the peloton, but
  the application is still there and remains useful for many people! We (or -
  mainly - I) don't have the human resources to keep up with everything and be
  ahead of all the things to do. Hence ...
</p>

<h3>Reducing/changing the scope of gedit</h3>
<p>
  gedit has for many years been between two things.
  (1) A great and easy-to-learn tool for beginners.
  And (2) some powerful plugins are or were available, so the text editor is
  also suitable for more advanced users, <em>also</em> in a professional
  context.
</p>
<p>
  So the scope of gedit is a bit unclear. What is clear is that we want from
  gedit something more than just writing quick notes. So something more than a
  simple notepad. But not as powerful and complete as Visual Studio Code (for
  instance, but you can pick your favorite IDE here, or Vim, Emacs).
</p>
<p>
  What is also clear for the path forward is a desire to well support markup
  languages like HTML, Markdown, etc. To support them <em>even better</em> than
  now, by adding some useful features for such languages.
</p>
<p>
  So in the context of the plugins removal, it means that some of them will
  <em>not</em> be re-implemented in C (or Rust or whatever). The set of features
  available through plugins will thus change. At least for the official plugins
  that are shipped with the gedit and gedit-plugins packages.
</p>

<h3>Did I mention Rust?</h3>
<p>
  Even though there is a desire to deal with less programming languages, ideally
  having a single-language project, there is <em>Rust</em>.
</p>
<p>
  Rust might be the exception. Maybe (without doing any promises), third-party
  plugins can choose Rust instead of C. That would make for a better experience.
  Then, maybe, a Rust third-party plugin will eventually find its course into
  gedit proper.
</p>

<h3>The impact for users</h3>
<p>
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit/-/commit/3e21148fb765fcbcc27d4a00a9bb905b1bfc7e1e">This commit</a>
  is the place to go to have the list of plugins that were implemented in Python
  and have been removed.
</p>
<p>
  But for the moment the
  <a href="https://flathub.org/apps/org.gnome.gedit">Flatpak of gedit</a>
  is mostly unaffected, because it can use the previous version of PyGObject
  while using the latest GNOME runtime.
</p>
<p>
  <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/store/apps/9NCQ8B0NVCW3">gedit on the Microsoft Store</a>
  is also unaffected.
</p>
<p>
  One day however, the updates of gedit and gedit-plugins will roll out.
  Versions >= 48.2 are already affected. The idea is to re-implement in C a few
  plugins so that the change is not too disruptive for Flatpak and Windows
  users.
</p>
<p>
  As a conclusion, let's see what the future of gedit has in stock! Be it
  attracting Rust developers, or being a tool of choice for certain uses,
  remaining humble at its task of being an easy-to-learn and general-purpose
  text editor.
</p>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind gedit.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Enter TeX</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-02-11-enter-tex.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-02-11-enter-tex.html" />
  <published>2025-02-11T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-02-11T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  As promised, I wanted to write a blog post about this application.
</p>
<p>
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/swilmet/enter-tex/">Enter TeX</a> is a
  <a href="https://tug.org/">TeX</a> /
  <a href="https://www.latex-project.org/">LaTeX</a>
  text editor previously named LaTeXila and then GNOME LaTeX. It is based on the
  same libraries as <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a>.
</p>

<h3>Renames</h3>
<p>
  LaTeXila was a fun name that I picked up when I was a student back in 2009.
  Then the project was renamed to GNOME LaTeX in 2017 but it was not a great
  choice because of the GNOME trademark. Now it is called <em>Enter TeX</em>.
</p>
<p>
  By having "TeX" in the name is more future-proof than "LaTeX", because there
  is also Plain TeX, <a href="https://wiki.contextgarden.net/">ConTeXt</a> and
  <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/texinfo/">GNU Texinfo</a>. Only LaTeX is
  currently well supported by Enter TeX, but the support for other variants
  would be a welcome addition.
</p>
<p>
  Note that the settings and configuration files are automatically migrated from
  LaTeXila or GNOME LaTeX to Enter TeX.
</p>
<p>
  There is another rename: the namespace for the C code has been changed from
  "Latexila" to "Gtex", to have a shorter and better name.
</p>

<h3>Other news</h3>
<p>
  If you're curious, you can read the top of the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/swilmet/enter-tex/-/blob/main/NEWS">NEWS file</a>,
  it has all the details.
</p>
<p>
  If I look at the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/swilmet/enter-tex/-/blob/main/docs/achievements.md">achievements file</a>,
  there is also the port from Autotools to Meson that was done recently and is
  worth mentioning.
</p>

<h3>Known issue for the icons</h3>
<p>
  Enter TeX unfortunately suffers from a combination of changes in
  adwaita-icon-theme and GThemedIcon (part of GIO). Link to the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/glib/-/issues/3376">issue on GitLab</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Compare the two screenshots and choose the one you prefer:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2025-02-11/screenshot1.png" target="_blank"><img src="images/2025-02-11/screenshot1.png" alt="screenshot 1" width="300" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2025-02-11/screenshot2.png" target="_blank"><img src="images/2025-02-11/screenshot2.png" alt="screenshot 2" width="300" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  As an interim solution, what I do is to install adwaita-icon-theme 41.0 in the
  same prefix as where Enter TeX is installed (not a system-wide prefix).
</p>

<h3>To summarize</h3>
<ul>
  <li>LaTeXila -> GNOME LaTeX -> Enter TeX</li>
  <li>C code namespace: Latexila -> Gtex</li>
  <li>Build system: Autotools -> Meson</li>
  <li>An old version of adwaita-icon-theme is necessary.</li>
</ul>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind Enter TeX.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Various news about gedit</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-01-07-various-news.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2025-01-07-various-news.html" />
  <published>2025-01-07T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2025-01-07T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  A new year begins, a good time to share some various news about
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a>.
</p>

<h3>gedit-text-editor.org</h3>
<p>
  gedit has a new domain name for its website:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit-text-editor.org</a>
</p>
<p>
  Previously, the gedit homepage was
  <a href="https://wiki.gnome.org/Apps/Gedit">on the GNOME wiki</a>,
  but the wiki has been retired. So a new website has been set up.
</p>
<p>
  Some work on the website is still necessary, especially to better support
  mobile devices (responsive web design), and also for printing the pages. If
  you are a seasoned web developer and want to contribute, don't hesitate to get
  in touch!
</p>

<h3>Wrapping-up statistics for 2024</h3>
<p>
  The total number of commits in gedit and gedit-related git repositories in
  2024 is: 1042. More precisely:
</p>
<pre>
300	enter-tex
365	gedit
52	gedit-plugins
50	gspell
13	libgedit-amtk
54	libgedit-gfls
47	libgedit-gtksourceview
161	libgedit-tepl
</pre>
<p>
  It counts all contributions, translation updates included.
</p>
<p>
  The list contains two apps, gedit and
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/swilmet/enter-tex">Enter TeX</a>.
  The rest are shared libraries (re-usable code available to create other text
  editors).
</p>
<p>
  Enter TeX is a TeX/LaTeX editor previously named LaTeXila and GNOME LaTeX.
  It depends on
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/technology.html">Gedit Technology</a>
  and drives some of its development. So it makes sense to include it alongside
  gedit. A blog post about Enter TeX will most probably be written, to shed some
  light on this project that started in 2009.
</p>

<h3>Onwards to 2025</h3>
<p>
  The development continues! To get the latest news, you can follow this blog
  or, alternatively, you can
  <a href="https://toot.community/@swilmet">follow me on Mastodon</a>.
</p>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind gedit.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>What's new in gedit 48</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-11-19-gedit-48.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-11-19-gedit-48.html" />
  <published>2024-11-19T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2024-11-19T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a> 48 has been
  released and is available on the three main desktop operating systems. Let's
  look at the highlights of this new version.
</p>

<h3>Dark theme</h3>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/thumbnail-gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the main window with dark theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  The <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-06-19-dark-theme-support-in-gedit.html">dark theme support</a>
  has already been covered.
</p>

<h3>World/gedit/ subgroup on GNOME's GitLab</h3>
<p>
  The main Git repositories of gedit are now all hosted under the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit">World/gedit/</a>
  subgroup on GNOME's GitLab. It currently includes gedit, gedit-plugins and all
  the libgedits.
</p>
<p>
  Previously, there was the problem that the libgedits - hosted on GitHub -
  didn't receive new translations. This is now resolved, all the relevant
  modules are on <a href="https://l10n.gnome.org/">l10n.gnome.org</a>. Thanks to
  the amazing work done by the GNOME translation teams, gedit is available in
  many languages with high quality translations!
</p>

<h3>Summary of changes for plugins</h3>
<p>
  Concerning the plugins, there is unfortunately a bad news. The following
  plugins have been removed:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>External Tools</li>
  <li>Git</li>
  <li>Quick Open</li>
  <li>Snippets</li>
</ul>

<p>
  There are several reasons:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    The primary reason is to have less code to maintain for the core gedit
    developers.
  </li>
  <li>
    Some of these plugins had bugs that made the application to crash. It is
    time consuming to investigate and properly fix such issues.
  </li>
  <li>
    And, it is always possible for other developers to bring a second life to a
    removed plugin, by copying the code into another repository. See the list of
    <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit/-/blob/master/plugins/third-party-plugins.md">third-party plugins</a>
    for some examples.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>Other changes</h3>
<ul>
  <li>
    The Text Size plugin has been promoted: it has been moved from the
    gedit-plugins repository to the main gedit repository, and is now enabled by
    default. So you can now zoom in and zoom out the text more easily.
  </li>
  <li>
    As always, there are a plethora of other little changes to improve the code
    quality.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>To conclude</h3>
<p>
  Don't hesitate to get in touch, be it for providing a general feedback, or for
  reporting specific issues, or for contributing.
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Dark theme support in gedit</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-06-19-dark-theme-support-in-gedit.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-06-19-dark-theme-support-in-gedit.html" />
  <published>2024-06-19T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2024-06-19T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  The development version of
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a> now has a
  much more complete support of light and dark themes, and switching between
  them from the desktop setting.
</p>

<h3>How it looks</h3>
<p>
  With the Solarized Dark color scheme for the main text area, and the Adwaita
  dark GTK theme:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/thumbnail-gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the main window with dark theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  The Preferences dialog:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-preferences-dialog.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-preferences-dialog.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the preferences dialog with dark theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-light-theme-preferences-dialog.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-light-theme-preferences-dialog.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the preferences dialog with light theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>

<h3>Possibilities and limitations</h3>
<p>
  It's possible to follow the system style (the desktop-wide setting that is
  applied to all the applications at once), or to force the light or dark theme
  variant.
</p>
<p>
  For the main text area a <em>color scheme</em> must be applied. There are thus
  <em>two</em> color schemes to choose: for the light versus dark theme
  variants, to automatically switch the color scheme.
</p>
<p>
  The Preferences dialog also allows you to choose a <em>dark</em> color scheme
  when a <em>light</em> theme variant is in effect, or vice-versa. If this was
  not possible, it would have been annoying to some people.
</p>
<p>
  There is however <strong>a minor limitation</strong>: the Classic and Tango
  color schemes are supported only with the light theme variant, because some
  colors are inherited from the theme and the other colors have been defined
  with a <em>light</em> theme in mind (see
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/issues/547">this issue on GitLab</a>
  with a screenshot of the text being unreadable).<br />
  So when the dark theme is applied, it is not possible to select Classic or
  Tango and their descriptions become "Unsupported for the dark theme variant"
  (by the way, it's better to keep them in the list and show an explanation; if
  Classic and Tango suddenly disappear from the list, you would have thought
  that there is a bug somewhere).
</p>
<p>
  It is also
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/commit/b655bd6bdf9b9fab1046960591fe823aa5aee16a">documented</a>
  in the user manual, if you're curious.
</p>

<h3>Technical details</h3>
<p>
  The heavy-lifting is done by
  <a href="https://gnome.pages.gitlab.gnome.org/libhandy/">libhandy</a>,
  and the actual dark theme (the Adwaita one) comes from
  <a href="https://gtk.org/">GTK</a> and its CSS engine.
</p>
<p>
  Some work was left to do in libgedit-gtksourceview for the color/style
  schemes; in libgedit-tepl for the components in the Preferences dialog plus a
  few other things; and finally in gedit to integrate what libgedit-tepl
  provides.
</p>
<p>
  In gedit there are now two GSettings keys for the color schemes, plus another
  key for the theme-variant, as can be seen in this <code>dconf watch</code>
  demo session:
</p>
<pre>
$ dconf watch /
/org/gnome/gedit/preferences/editor/style-scheme-for-dark-theme-variant
  'oblivion'

/org/gnome/gedit/preferences/ui/theme-variant
  'light'

/org/gnome/gedit/preferences/editor/style-scheme-for-light-theme-variant
  'classic'
</pre>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>
  This feature was asked by many people and it's finally there. It will be
  available in gedit 48, the next stable version to be released soon if
  everything goes well.
</p>
<p>
  Do not hesitate to
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">get in touch</a>
  and provide a feedback, be it for this feature or for other things.
</p>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main gedit
  developer.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>gedit 47 released and packaged</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-24-gedit-47-released-and-packaged.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-24-gedit-47-released-and-packaged.html" />
  <published>2024-05-24T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2024-05-24T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a> 47 has been
  released and packaged recently.
</p>

<h3>What's new</h3>
<p>
  The <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-04-26-change-of-icons-and-logo-for-gedit.html">change of icons and logo</a>
  was already explained.
</p>

<h4>Dark GTK theme support - some progress</h4>
<p>
  There is some progress to better support the dark GTK theme variant. On Linux
  you can use the <a href="https://apps.gnome.org/DconfEditor/">Dconf Editor</a>
  application or the <code>gsettings</code> command in a terminal to change
  gedit to use the dark theme:
</p>
<pre>
$ gsettings get org.gnome.gedit.preferences.ui theme-variant
'light'
$ gsettings set org.gnome.gedit.preferences.ui theme-variant "'dark'"

# To reset to the default value:
$ gsettings reset org.gnome.gedit.preferences.ui theme-variant
</pre>
<p>
  Some more work is necessary to finish this feature. It is planned to add a
  'system' setting, to follow the desktop config. To adapt the Preferences
  dialog. And to avoid showing bugs with color schemes that don't support dark
  GTK themes (classic and tango), or to fix those color schemes (but since they
  inherit colors from the GTK theme, it is currently expected that these colors
  come from a <em>light</em> theme).
</p>

<h4>For plugin developers: improved API documentation</h4>
<p>
  The main classes of gedit are now much better
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/developer-docs/gedit/">documented</a>.
</p>

<h4>Translations temporarily disabled</h4>
<p>
  Unfortunately, the translations (or localization, l10n) is temporarily
  disabled. So gedit is available in English only. (You can still write
  documents in any language thanks to the Unicode support, of course).
</p>
<p>
  This is because the Gedit Technology modules that are hosted on GitHub need
  something else than <a href="https://l10n.gnome.org/">l10n.gnome.org</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Work is being done to address this issue. One translation platform has already
  been tested but was not really satisfactory, so another platform is currently
  being tested at the time of writing this.
</p>

<h4>Refactoring and making more code re-usable, as always</h4>
<p>
  Code refactoring is necessary for gedit. Cleaner code permits to better see
  bugs, to fix them and (hopefully) prevent them from re-appearing in the
  future.
</p>

<h3>Packaging work</h3>
<p>
  gedit is
  <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/store/apps/9NCQ8B0NVCW3">available on the Microsoft Store</a>.
  It is a way to finance the project, so every purchase helps.
</p>
<p>
  For Linux, the latest gedit is
  <a href="https://flathub.org/apps/org.gnome.gedit">available on Flathub</a>.
  It finally has the Verified badge, and the Flatpak is now directly updated by
  the upstream developers.
</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>
  Contrarily to what is sometimes expected from a software release, this is
  unfortunately not the best gedit release ever because of the transition for
  the translation platform. gedit 48 will be a better version in that regard.
</p>
<p>
  We wanted to release a new version instead of waiting more, because we prefer
  more iterations instead of bigger releases. For a project like gedit, it's
  sometimes a bit a rocky road to drive the project further. On the brighter
  side, gedit should be more robust overall (the code has seen some bug fixes
  and many small code improvements under the hood).
</p>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind gedit.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>History of Gedit Technology</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-15-history-of-gedit-technology.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-15-history-of-gedit-technology.html" />
  <published>2024-05-15T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2024-05-15T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  The website of
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/technology.html">Gedit Technology</a>
  has been created in 2022 and is now hosted where the link points to. However,
  the actual code behind it is older than that. Read on for a retrospective and
  the important dates and milestones.
</p>

<h3>What is Gedit Technology</h3>
<p>
  First, what is it? The project web page describes it this way:
</p>
<blockquote>
  Gedit Technology is based on the GTK graphical toolkit and provides the main
  components behind the gedit text editor.
</blockquote>
<p>
  <em>gedit</em> is the application (for end users), <em>Gedit Technology</em>
  is the re-usable code provided as a set of libraries (for developers).
</p>

<h3>The libraries</h3>
<p>
  gedit is closely related to some libraries. The list, alongside the year of
  the project creation:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>2001: GtkSourceView (libgedit-gtksourceview)</li>
  <li>2009: libpeas</li>
  <li>2015: gspell</li>
  <li>2016: libgedit-tepl</li>
  <li>2018: libgedit-amtk</li>
  <li>2023: libgedit-gfls</li>
</ul>
<p>
  Initially, GtkSourceView didn't come from the gedit codebase, but once created
  gedit has quickly adopted it. Then the two projects were developed side by
  side. Its main feature is syntax highlighting, but lots of other features have
  been added over the years (small ones like displaying the line numbers in the
  margin, and bigger ones such as a completion framework).
</p>
<p>
  libpeas is the plugin engine, used by other applications like the Totem video
  player. It is a gedit developer who decided to factor out a library from the
  gedit codebase. Before that, application authors copied (and modified) the
  implementation from another app, so in GNOME there were lots of different
  variants.
</p>
<p>
  gspell is for the spell-checking. Its code comes from a gedit plugin. The
  plugin still exists but is much smaller now. The purpose was to share code
  between gedit and GNOME LaTeX (another text editor that targets the TeX/LaTeX
  languages). The gspell library has been used by numerous other GTK
  applications, including GNOME Software (the software center).
</p>
<p>
  libgedit-tepl is not as widespread as the other projects, but is the
  continuation of GtkSourceView with more experimental APIs. The goal is to be
  able to iterate on the APIs more freely.
</p>
<p>
  libgedit-amtk and libgedit-gfls are small additional libraries. The first one
  is all about Actions, Menus and Toolbars (Kit). The second one is about File
  Loading and Saving but is in its early infancy.
</p>

<h3>About the "libgedit" prefix</h3>
<p>
  Note the "libgedit" prefix. Some projects were first created without it and
  have been renamed since. The prefix permits to better identify the project
  origins or to what it belongs. Since the number of such projects was growing,
  having more and more disparate names was not really convenient, especially for
  packagers.
</p>
<p>
  Now on an up-to-date Linux distribution, you can search the packages database
  for "gedit" or "libgedit". Or during updates, if you see "libgedit-something",
  you know what it is.
</p>

<h3>Re-usability, API and documentation</h3>
<p>
  The more recent developments in gedit focused on re-usability and refactoring.
  By doing this little exercise, we believe that the code has a better quality:
  a better architecture (most importantly), smaller classes with more separation
  of concerns, fewer bugs, more unit-testable code (and unit-tested), and much
  improved
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/developer-docs/">documentation</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Thank you for reading!
</p>
<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind Gedit Technology.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Change of icons and logo for gedit</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-04-26-change-of-icons-and-logo-for-gedit.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-04-26-change-of-icons-and-logo-for-gedit.html" />
  <published>2024-04-26T10:00:00Z</published>
  <updated>2024-04-26T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  There will be a change of icons and logo for
  <a href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/">gedit</a> 47.
</p>

<p>Some dates:</p>
<ul>
  <li>September 2018: new icon for gedit and other GNOME apps.</li>
  <li>March 2024: restore to the previous design.</li>
</ul>

<p>The current icon, restored from a previous design:</p>
<p><img src="images/gedit-icon-current.png" alt="Current gedit icon" width="128" /></p>

<p>The old icon (2018-2024):</p>
<p><img src="images/gedit-icon-old.svg" alt="Old gedit icon" width="128" /></p>

<p>
  The
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/commit/d444f3e6ebd42e1a9c7a58edf039667a8b472277">git commit</a>
  message has all the details for the reasons of the change. Namely, the old
  icon had several disadvantages:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    The pencil was too big.
  </li>
  <li>
    The blue color at the bottom was barely visible, especially at small sizes.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  The current design has actually <em>several</em> icons that are tailored for
  different sizes.
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/tree/master/data/icons">All the icons</a>
  have been restored.
</p>

<p>
  The logo has also been restored and is present in the About dialog window:
</p>
<p><img src="images/gedit-about-dialog.png" alt="gedit About window" /></p>

<p>
  To avoid any confusion, only the icons and logo that represent the
  <em>application</em> (gedit) are affected. All the other icons used within
  gedit remain the same (for example to represent a directory or a printer) and
  rely on the icon theme used (it's a desktop-wide setting).
</p>

<p>
  I hope that you will appreciate the change of design :)
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
