<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <author>
    <name>Gedit Technology</name>
  </author>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/feed.atom.xml</id>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/feed.atom.xml" />
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/index.html" />
  <title>Gedit Technology</title>
  <updated>2024-11-19T10:00:00Z</updated>

<entry>
  <title>What's new in gedit 48</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-11-19-gedit-48.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-11-19-gedit-48.html" />
  <updated>2024-11-19T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/apps/gedit/">gedit</a> 48 has been
  released and is available on the three main desktop operating systems. Let's
  look at the highlights of this new version.
</p>

<h3>Dark theme</h3>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/thumbnail-gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the main window with dark theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  The <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/blog/2024-06-19-dark-theme-support-in-gedit.html">dark theme support</a>
  has already been covered.
</p>

<h3>World/gedit/ subgroup on GNOME's GitLab</h3>
<p>
  The main Git repositories of gedit are now all hosted under the
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit">World/gedit/</a>
  subgroup on GNOME's GitLab. It currently includes gedit, gedit-plugins and all
  the libgedits.
</p>
<p>
  Previously, there was the problem that the libgedits - hosted on GitHub -
  didn't receive new translations. This is now resolved, all the relevant
  modules are on <a href="https://l10n.gnome.org/">l10n.gnome.org</a>. Thanks to
  the amazing work done by the GNOME translation teams, gedit is available in
  many languages with high quality translations!
</p>

<h3>Summary of changes for plugins</h3>
<p>
  Concerning the plugins, there is unfortunately a bad news. The following
  plugins have been removed:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>External Tools</li>
  <li>Git</li>
  <li>Quick Open</li>
  <li>Snippets</li>
</ul>

<p>
  There are several reasons:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    The primary reason is to have less code to maintain for the core gedit
    developers.
  </li>
  <li>
    Some of these plugins had bugs that made the application to crash. It is
    time consuming to investigate and properly fix such issues.
  </li>
  <li>
    And, it is always possible for other developers to bring a second life to a
    removed plugin, by copying the code into another repository. See the list of
    <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/World/gedit/gedit/-/blob/master/plugins/third-party-plugins.md">third-party plugins</a>
    for some examples.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>Other changes</h3>
<ul>
  <li>
    The Text Size plugin has been promoted: it has been moved from the
    gedit-plugins repository to the main gedit repository, and is now enabled by
    default. So you can now zoom in and zoom out the text more easily.
  </li>
  <li>
    As always, there are a plethora of other little changes to improve the code
    quality.
  </li>
</ul>

<h3>To conclude</h3>
<p>
  Don't hesitate to get in touch, be it for providing a general feedback, or for
  reporting specific issues, or for contributing.
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Dark theme support in gedit</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-06-19-dark-theme-support-in-gedit.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-06-19-dark-theme-support-in-gedit.html" />
  <updated>2024-06-19T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  The development version of
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/apps/gedit/">gedit</a> now has a
  much more complete support of light and dark themes, and switching between
  them from the desktop setting.
</p>

<h3>How it looks</h3>
<p>
  With the Solarized Dark color scheme for the main text area, and the Adwaita
  dark GTK theme:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/thumbnail-gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-main-window.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the main window with dark theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  The Preferences dialog:
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-preferences-dialog.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-dark-theme-preferences-dialog.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the preferences dialog with dark theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>
<p>
  <a href="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-light-theme-preferences-dialog.png" target="_blank"><img
    src="images/2024-06-19/gedit-screenshot-light-theme-preferences-dialog.png"
    alt="gedit screenshot of the preferences dialog with light theme"
    width="250" /></a>
</p>

<h3>Possibilities and limitations</h3>
<p>
  It's possible to follow the system style (the desktop-wide setting that is
  applied to all the applications at once), or to force the light or dark theme
  variant.
</p>
<p>
  For the main text area a <em>color scheme</em> must be applied. There are thus
  <em>two</em> color schemes to choose: for the light versus dark theme
  variants, to automatically switch the color scheme.
</p>
<p>
  The Preferences dialog also allows you to choose a <em>dark</em> color scheme
  when a <em>light</em> theme variant is in effect, or vice-versa. If this was
  not possible, it would have been annoying to some people.
</p>
<p>
  There is however <strong>a minor limitation</strong>: the Classic and Tango
  color schemes are supported only with the light theme variant, because some
  colors are inherited from the theme and the other colors have been defined
  with a <em>light</em> theme in mind (see
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/issues/547">this issue on GitLab</a>
  with a screenshot of the text being unreadable).<br />
  So when the dark theme is applied, it is not possible to select Classic or
  Tango and their descriptions become "Unsupported for the dark theme variant"
  (by the way, it's better to keep them in the list and show an explanation; if
  Classic and Tango suddenly disappear from the list, you would have thought
  that there is a bug somewhere).
</p>
<p>
  It is also
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/commit/b655bd6bdf9b9fab1046960591fe823aa5aee16a">documented</a>
  in the user manual, if you're curious.
</p>

<h3>Technical details</h3>
<p>
  The heavy-lifting is done by
  <a href="https://gnome.pages.gitlab.gnome.org/libhandy/">libhandy</a>,
  and the actual dark theme (the Adwaita one) comes from
  <a href="https://gtk.org/">GTK</a> and its CSS engine.
</p>
<p>
  Some work was left to do in libgedit-gtksourceview for the color/style
  schemes; in libgedit-tepl for the components in the Preferences dialog plus a
  few other things; and finally in gedit to integrate what libgedit-tepl
  provides.
</p>
<p>
  In gedit there are now two GSettings keys for the color schemes, plus another
  key for the theme-variant, as can be seen in this <code>dconf watch</code>
  demo session:
</p>
<pre>
$ dconf watch /
/org/gnome/gedit/preferences/editor/style-scheme-for-dark-theme-variant
  'oblivion'

/org/gnome/gedit/preferences/ui/theme-variant
  'light'

/org/gnome/gedit/preferences/editor/style-scheme-for-light-theme-variant
  'classic'
</pre>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>
  This feature was asked by many people and it's finally there. It will be
  available in gedit 48, the next stable version to be released soon if
  everything goes well.
</p>
<p>
  Do not hesitate to
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/apps/gedit/">get in touch</a>
  and provide a feedback, be it for this feature or for other things.
</p>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main gedit
  developer.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>gedit 47 released and packaged</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-24-gedit-47-released-and-packaged.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-24-gedit-47-released-and-packaged.html" />
  <updated>2024-05-24T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/apps/gedit/">gedit</a> 47 has been
  released and packaged recently.
</p>

<h3>What's new</h3>
<p>
  The <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/blog/2024-04-26-change-of-icons-and-logo-for-gedit.html">change of icons and logo</a>
  was already explained.
</p>

<h4>Dark GTK theme support - some progress</h4>
<p>
  There is some progress to better support the dark GTK theme variant. On Linux
  you can use the <a href="https://apps.gnome.org/DconfEditor/">Dconf Editor</a>
  application or the <code>gsettings</code> command in a terminal to change
  gedit to use the dark theme:
</p>
<pre>
$ gsettings get org.gnome.gedit.preferences.ui theme-variant
'light'
$ gsettings set org.gnome.gedit.preferences.ui theme-variant "'dark'"

# To reset to the default value:
$ gsettings reset org.gnome.gedit.preferences.ui theme-variant
</pre>
<p>
  Some more work is necessary to finish this feature. It is planned to add a
  'system' setting, to follow the desktop config. To adapt the Preferences
  dialog. And to avoid showing bugs with color schemes that don't support dark
  GTK themes (classic and tango), or to fix those color schemes (but since they
  inherit colors from the GTK theme, it is currently expected that these colors
  come from a <em>light</em> theme).
</p>

<h4>For plugin developers: improved API documentation</h4>
<p>
  The main classes of gedit are now much better
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/developer-docs/gedit/">documented</a>.
</p>

<h4>Translations temporarily disabled</h4>
<p>
  Unfortunately, the translations (or localization, l10n) is temporarily
  disabled. So gedit is available in English only. (You can still write
  documents in any language thanks to the Unicode support, of course).
</p>
<p>
  This is because the Gedit Technology modules that are hosted on GitHub need
  something else than <a href="https://l10n.gnome.org/">l10n.gnome.org</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Work is being done to address this issue. One translation platform has already
  been tested but was not really satisfactory, so another platform is currently
  being tested at the time of writing this.
</p>

<h4>Refactoring and making more code re-usable, as always</h4>
<p>
  Code refactoring is necessary for gedit. Cleaner code permits to better see
  bugs, to fix them and (hopefully) prevent them from re-appearing in the
  future.
</p>

<h3>Packaging work</h3>
<p>
  gedit is
  <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/store/apps/9NCQ8B0NVCW3">available on the Microsoft Store</a>.
  It is a way to finance the project, so every purchase helps.
</p>
<p>
  For Linux, the latest gedit is
  <a href="https://flathub.org/apps/org.gnome.gedit">available on Flathub</a>.
  It finally has the Verified badge, and the Flatpak is now directly updated by
  the upstream developers.
</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>
  Contrarily to what is sometimes expected from a software release, this is
  unfortunately not the best gedit release ever because of the transition for
  the translation platform. gedit 48 will be a better version in that regard.
</p>
<p>
  We wanted to release a new version instead of waiting more, because we prefer
  more iterations instead of bigger releases. For a project like gedit, it's
  sometimes a bit a rocky road to drive the project further. On the brighter
  side, gedit should be more robust overall (the code has seen some bug fixes
  and many small code improvements under the hood).
</p>

<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind gedit.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>History of Gedit Technology</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-15-history-of-gedit-technology.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-05-15-history-of-gedit-technology.html" />
  <updated>2024-05-15T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  The website of
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/">Gedit Technology</a>
  has been created in 2022 and is now hosted where the link points to. However,
  the actual code behind it is older than that. Read on for a retrospective and
  the important dates and milestones.
</p>

<h3>What is Gedit Technology</h3>
<p>
  First, what is it? The project web page describes it this way:
</p>
<blockquote>
  Gedit Technology is based on the GTK graphical toolkit and provides the main
  components behind the gedit text editor.
</blockquote>
<p>
  <em>gedit</em> is the application (for end users), <em>Gedit Technology</em>
  is the re-usable code provided as a set of libraries (for developers).
</p>

<h3>The libraries</h3>
<p>
  gedit is closely related to some libraries. The list, alongside the year of
  the project creation:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>2001: GtkSourceView (libgedit-gtksourceview)</li>
  <li>2009: libpeas</li>
  <li>2015: gspell</li>
  <li>2016: libgedit-tepl</li>
  <li>2018: libgedit-amtk</li>
  <li>2023: libgedit-gfls</li>
</ul>
<p>
  Initially, GtkSourceView didn't come from the gedit codebase, but once created
  gedit has quickly adopted it. Then the two projects were developed side by
  side. Its main feature is syntax highlighting, but lots of other features have
  been added over the years (small ones like displaying the line numbers in the
  margin, and bigger ones such as a completion framework).
</p>
<p>
  libpeas is the plugin engine, used by other applications like the Totem video
  player. It is a gedit developer who decided to factor out a library from the
  gedit codebase. Before that, application authors copied (and modified) the
  implementation from another app, so in GNOME there were lots of different
  variants.
</p>
<p>
  gspell is for the spell-checking. Its code comes from a gedit plugin. The
  plugin still exists but is much smaller now. The purpose was to share code
  between gedit and GNOME LaTeX (another text editor that targets the TeX/LaTeX
  languages). The gspell library has been used by numerous other GTK
  applications, including GNOME Software (the software center).
</p>
<p>
  libgedit-tepl is not as widespread as the other projects, but is the
  continuation of GtkSourceView with more experimental APIs. The goal is to be
  able to iterate on the APIs more freely.
</p>
<p>
  libgedit-amtk and libgedit-gfls are small additional libraries. The first one
  is all about Actions, Menus and Toolbars (Kit). The second one is about File
  Loading and Saving but is in its early infancy.
</p>

<h3>About the "libgedit" prefix</h3>
<p>
  Note the "libgedit" prefix. Some projects were first created without it and
  have been renamed since. The prefix permits to better identify the project
  origins or to what it belongs. Since the number of such projects was growing,
  having more and more disparate names was not really convenient, especially for
  packagers.
</p>
<p>
  Now on an up-to-date Linux distribution, you can search the packages database
  for "gedit" or "libgedit". Or during updates, if you see "libgedit-something",
  you know what it is.
</p>

<h3>Re-usability, API and documentation</h3>
<p>
  The more recent developments in gedit focused on re-usability and refactoring.
  By doing this little exercise, we believe that the code has a better quality:
  a better architecture (most importantly), smaller classes with more separation
  of concerns, fewer bugs, more unit-testable code (and unit-tested), and much
  improved
  <a href="https://gedit-technology.github.io/developer-docs/">documentation</a>.
</p>
<p>
  Thank you for reading!
</p>
<p><small>
  This article was written by Sébastien Wilmet, currently the main developer
  behind Gedit Technology.
</small></p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

<entry>
  <title>Change of icons and logo for gedit</title>
  <id>https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-04-26-change-of-icons-and-logo-for-gedit.html</id>
  <link type="text/html" href="https://gedit-text-editor.org/blog/2024-04-26-change-of-icons-and-logo-for-gedit.html" />
  <updated>2024-04-26T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <content type="xhtml">
    <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>
  There will be a change of icons and logo for gedit 47.
</p>

<p>Some dates:</p>
<ul>
  <li>September 2018: new icon for gedit and other GNOME apps.</li>
  <li>March 2024: restore to the previous design.</li>
</ul>

<p>The current icon, restored from a previous design:</p>
<p><img src="images/gedit-icon-current.png" alt="Current gedit icon" width="128" /></p>

<p>The old icon (2018-2024):</p>
<p><img src="images/gedit-icon-old.svg" alt="Old gedit icon" width="128" /></p>

<p>
  The
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/commit/d444f3e6ebd42e1a9c7a58edf039667a8b472277">git commit</a>
  message has all the details for the reasons of the change. Namely, the old
  icon had several disadvantages:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>
    The pencil was too big.
  </li>
  <li>
    The blue color at the bottom was barely visible, especially at small sizes.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
  The current design has actually <em>several</em> icons that are tailored for
  different sizes.
  <a href="https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/gedit/-/tree/master/data/icons">All the icons</a>
  have been restored.
</p>

<p>
  The logo has also been restored and is present in the About dialog window:
</p>
<p><img src="images/gedit-about-dialog.png" alt="gedit About window" /></p>

<p>
  To avoid any confusion, only the icons and logo that represent the
  <em>application</em> (gedit) are affected. All the other icons used within
  gedit remain the same (for example to represent a directory or a printer) and
  rely on the icon theme used (it's a desktop-wide setting).
</p>

<p>
  I hope that you will appreciate the change of design :)
</p>
    </div>
  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
